suppose we are given a circle with
radius r so that its area is a equals pi
r squared
let's paint half the circumference blue
and then roll the circle one half turn
so that we are left with a line of
length pi times r
extend the line by the length of the
radius r and we get a semicircle of
diameter pi r plus r
then create the half chord from the
bottom of the original circle to the
larger semicircle and call its length x
connecting the ends of the diameter to
the end of this half chord results in a
right triangle according to thaley's
triangle theorem
consequently the two subtriangles with
side length x are similar
this implies that pi r over x
equals
x
over r
therefore
x squared equals pi r squared
we can also use the half chord to create
a square with side length x so that its
area
is a equals x squared
but x squared equals pi r squared and
thus we have constructed a square with
the same area as the given circle
that is to say we have squared the
circle
[Music]
you